
Forgiving your enemies

by Paulo Coelho on June 27, 2012

The abbot asked his favorite pupil how his spiritual progress was coming along. The pupil answered that he was managing to dedicate to God each and every moment of the day.

“Then all that’s left now is to forgive your enemies.”

The young man was shocked:

“But I’m not angry at my enemies!”

“Do you think God is angry at you?”

“Of course not!”

“And even so you ask Him to forgive you, don’t you? Do the same with your enemies, even though you don’t feel hatred for them.
“Those who practice forgiveness wash and perfume their own hearts.”



!@#$%^&*()  COMMENTS



Mohammad Ali Gaad July 26, 2012 at 3:56 pm

    Yeah first we should make our heart pious and lovable before we ask God to forgive our committed sins.

   
Deborah July 23, 2012 at 4:39 am

    How do you forgive when you’re not angry at them? They won’t be in mind; and I won’t be considering them enemies as well…

   
Jack July 22, 2012 at 4:25 pm

    Como perdonar, si eso implica olvidar? Como desprenderse del dolor causado por otros cuando esta afectando tu presente por los danos hecho. Olvidar como lo hago, perdonar ? volver algun dia a hablarles? No se es muy dificil con tanto dolor, y he tratado de dejar eso en el pasado.

  
miriam ferns July 22, 2012 at 2:25 pm

    i forgive Daren but i do wonder that if i forgive too well,i may just forget what detriment they caused me. I find forgiving people who still would love to cause me max.harm given half a chance such as norbert and who talk ill of me to my son too hard to forgive at present…so…what can one do about this?

   
Ladyday July 13, 2012 at 6:11 pm

    I can forgive some people because I know the underlying cause of their actions. I guess their actions are not excused but justifiable. It doesn’t mean I have them in my life however.
    Some people I just choose to forget rather than forgive because it’s easier for my mind and nerves to handle. They don’t care if I forgive them or not because I mean nothing to them or because of ego. Some people don’t want my forgiveness because they believe they have done nothing wrong.

    I don’t mean them harm, it’s funny because I’m too tired to even wish my enemies (do they even exist? of course) bad sentiment, I’ve struggled enough that I wouldn’t wish my bad onto anyone.

   
Martha Alencar July 13, 2012 at 3:24 am

    O perdão mais difícil de ceder tem sido, não aos meus “inimigos”, pois destes nada tenho a perdoar. Não estou acima deles, nem sou um ser tão especial para isso. Já perdoar a mim não tem sido fácil. hehehehe

    Grande abraço!

    Boa caminhada ;)
    …conhecer trechos da tua tem ajudado em curvas da minha! Por tal, obrigada!


Pandora July 9, 2012 at 12:33 pm

    Yesterday, I received an abusive Twitter message from someone who writes regularly on this blog. They have never met me, never spoken with me, are not a Facebook “Friend”, and yet their message was filled with such vitriol and hatred towards me, that I was left with the question: “Why should this person, who doesn’t know me at all, who writes on the blog in such a different manner, try to ruin my afternoon in this way?”

    And then of course I realised that he was projecting his own self loathing on to me.

    What words people say, and how they set out to deceive, but the true test of a wolf in sheep’s clothing is that through there acts they make themselves known, even though they think no-one else may be watching them.

    So as the parable goes:

    Not by my own will but the shepherd’s folly.
    The beast reared by me will make me his prey,
    For gratitude cannot change nature.

    So this brings me to a question, when a person chooses to behave in a base manner to deliberately cut out their humane side, are they capable of receiving, desiring or seeking forgiveness?

    I love wolves, love cats and dogs all prey hunters, even though I don’t understand their behaviour, it is not necessary for me to forgive them they are behaving as they should, I would expect nothing less – but from a fellow human – I hope for more.

    To forgive someone who shows no sense of remorse, just to “set myself free”, is inappropriate, I am not bound by anyone’s unprovoked acts of hatred or violence towards me, after all they (the perpetrator) have ultimately acted against themselves. Instead I prefer to Accept, Bless, Release, ask for divine intervention and where appropriate Block.

    Thank you for this blog Paulo, it is a blessing to me really, as are the many, many, genuine friends I have met here – of which there are many.

 

    Paulo Coelho July 10, 2012 at 6:35 pm

        we already blocked him

    Annie July 10, 2012 at 6:55 pm

        Not to be naive, but possibly – please don’t exclude this possibility- it’s a matter of misunderstanding and/or misusing words…
        Words can be tricky, and if one uses a language that is not his native one, it might get weird…

        Love to you Pandora

        Love and Gratitude
        Annie

    Pandora July 30, 2012 at 7:45 pm

        Dear Annie

        I can understand your naivety, it took me some time to rationalise what had happened, and I would much rather of believed that this was the case, but I felt his intention behind the words was malevolent.

        My instinct was right, as I discovered that I was not the only one who had been affected, although I didn’t know this at the time I wrote the original posting. This therefore eliminates conclusively the remotest possibility of doubt about it being a mistranslation and/or misinterpretation issue.

        Words can be used as weapons – double edged and fork tongued, they can be used to harm or to heal… bless or curse and we choose our adversary not the other way round.

        You are most welcome to contact me directly.

        With love
        Pandora

Katie (My Mother Killed Christ) July 6, 2012 at 2:40 pm

    Forgiveness for others, and most importantly… for myself, was the final step to forever free myself from the contraints of the past.

  
Chrissy Divine July 3, 2012 at 4:54 pm

    True food for the soul is Love. This is where we should start, the closest to that is our very own heart. What people need first of foremost is for the great love that resides in their hearts to be awoken. I wrote a rather wonderful post on Forgiveness (http://www.prodigyofexistence.com/2012/07/03/true-forgiveness/). Would you do me the absolute honor of reading it? It starts like this: My sweet darling, before you are all goodness, all love (which you already know you are perceptually, but you still need to actually fully experience it), before you can truly move on with your life (to fulfill your destiny, to reach a higher state of feeling, to feel good, ecstatic) you are to let go of all of the past, all its negative content, to forgive yourself, and all others, for all damage you think you might have done. [...] True Forgiveness is yours to give and to receive. I love you with all my heart.



    Dave C July 3, 2012 at 9:17 pm

        I do concur, that was a wonderful post. And then, there it could be, the secret of our existence ? The answer to all traditions and paths; that Love unconditional is the deliverer, our redemption. Chrissy, you say love thyself, with understanding , patience, and forgiveness so that all others can feel and receive that blessing through proximity. That love is then a contagion to be spread and shared as it manifests itself from the hidden (darkness) to the full expression, or Light. I am gratefull for your words, and feelings Chrissy, so well stated.

Caroline July 3, 2012 at 2:19 pm

    Forgiving in my opinion is acknowledging that the person is human and human is to error and hence let the grudge take care of itself. And dont let anyone make it hard by telling you to forgive and forget
    http://vitaminforthesoul.blogspot.com/2010/10/forgive-and-let-god-do-rest-by-joseph.html
    //if someone does something to you they take some power from you. if you dont forgive them they keep the power~Madea

 
phuongsong July 3, 2012 at 9:59 am

    forgiveness is easy word to say but hard to do, by how? peace is result of forgiveness

 
Heimo Alexander Kruschinski June 29, 2012 at 6:02 pm

    What i believe is simple Annie. What i think is another question. I love your thoughts and one of the mainpersons of my story too.

    I wish you a wonderful day

 
TRUTH NEEDS NO SUPPORT IS ALWAYS THE ULTIMATE WINNER .... June 29, 2012 at 6:07 am

    Its not vanity or overconfidence you will find in my words …. Its the power of Truth …. Raw and bare naked Truth…… needs no ornaments or adjectives to its support .


Bliss of forgiving...... June 29, 2012 at 3:55 am

    This is what forgiving is ….. Each and every word speaks of the Ecstacy …. Love ….. Beauty of Forgiving and being Forgiven….its connection our souls through the soul of universe ….Paulo you must be realising that i am also cherishing the same mental state you are…… which is going to last for ever and ever …..

 
Bliss of forgiving...... June 29, 2012 at 3:54 am

    This is what forgiving is ….. Each and every word speaks of the Ecstacy …. Love ….. Beauty of Forgiving and being Forgiven….its connection our souls through the soul of universe ….Paulo you must be realising that i am also Enjoying the same mental state you are…… which is going to last for ever and ever …..

 
You are going to Hold On something for your entire life which will not let you live peacefully ..... June 29, 2012 at 3:30 am

    Its still time try searching your soul . You will definitely find it . I have been time and again telling that you can not create something out of nothing . It is as simple as it looks . Go through my activities in life , relations with any one , whether be a friend or relatives or unknown . Study it carefully without prejudiced mind . Go through my each and every work of my blog . Go and ask people my friends who know me and my spouse too.
    Ones crooked and prevert mind can reach to any any weird absurd illogical conclusions . I was not coming directly to this which i am able to sense since last few days . I neednot to provide clarifications in front of any such people who do not have any sense of proportion or rationality in their thinking … As it is not going to help … They will again start making new calculations and interpretations of my clarifying things . I leave it on to them . I have a very good social status . People love me.
    And I DONT CARE FOR THOSE WHO THINK SO WILD* ITS THEIR EVIL BRAINS THEY ARE FREE TO THINK & IT DOESNT EFFECT ME ANYWHERE AS I KNOW MY WIFE KNOWS WHATS THE TRUTH ( these are only *who are far far away from me my place are the only ones who have such inhuman thinking about me ) I DONT WANT TO HAVE ANY RELATIONSHIPS WITH THEM AS THEY ARE NOT WORTH IT

    There are chances though very scarce that if you people except mr Paulo if you ever meet your innerself ie your soul ask this from it ….you will get the reply ….and that day you may repent for your such a sinful act done on someone innocent . I am free and my mind is totally clear do you know why …. Truth needs no proof …. Needs no support as it alone is enough … Millions of lies can not create a single truth …..
    I was only guilty for having a small infatuation affair or whatsoever ….that too it was Mr Paulo who brought me back to the right path …. My wife never came to know about it as it was only for a few days …. It has nothing to do with the accident ….. What i can do for people who think themselves as GOD are master meditators have attained achieving The Third Eye of Lord Shiva … .. Its
    Height of COMPASSION which can be seen and felt in their thoughts……. I am going totally free and light as i dont have any thing in my mind …. I am living an absolute peaceful life ….. I strongly believe in God …. Pray to God to Forgive them and provide me enough strength to forgive them for this unforgivable act of theirs…. Mr Paulo i have not written any thing for you as i know you are really connected to your innerself have got the clear vision of the soul of universe ….

   

    toñi July 1, 2012 at 3:59 pm

        Si realmente se siente usted tan puro y limpio no sé porqué escribe todo esto.
        Si usted era responsable de una historia de amor de unos días y no se siente responsable del accidente, no comprendo porque piensa en ello.
        Lo que quedó en el pasado se quedó en el pasado y punto.
        No necesita dar explicaciones de nada.
        Hay muchas historias de amor de unos días y muchos accidentes en la historia de las personas. ¿sabes qué ocurre? que somos responsables de nuestros accidentes, y si no lo somos…entonces es mejor olvidar el asunto, porque siempre ocurre que la otra parte del “accidente” acaba olvidando el tema y cuando queremos dar explicaciones a la otra parte del accidente, esa otra parte no quiere saber nada del tema.
        Un saludo y que sea muy feliz.

Lyl June 28, 2012 at 9:37 pm

    Ennemies?Where?Unless you’re in politic or mafia or a gang,I don’t see where that strong word can apply in real life..and if some people give themselves this title,it’s their problem,they watched too much the Godfather.

  
Serenity June 28, 2012 at 5:59 pm

    I would just like to share a very interesting read.

    http://jahtruth.net/wayad.htm
    Then go to The way Home.

    Seek and you shall find..

    Love & Light

 
Raphael June 28, 2012 at 5:31 pm

    Life is very short, and there’s no time for fussing and fighting my friends. – John Lennon.

    Nós temos tantos problemas já no mundo que se ficarmos construindo os nossos como se fizessem parte tão importante do mundo, acabaremos nos esquecemos dos que realmente importam.
    Um abraço com carinho, Raphael.

 
luis fernando reyes June 28, 2012 at 3:14 pm

    Perdonar, pero no olvidar; eso nos forma carácter.

  
Corina June 28, 2012 at 3:08 pm

    Well, I think the very first step should be to forgive yourself. It means stop regreting, stop blaming yourself, stop crying for lake of reaction or too much reaction. It means to accept. Both rationally and emotionally.
    Then we should forgive our friends. Their betrayel, lies… are human… or not.
    Then it’s just a piece of cake to forgive your enemies. It’s their job to hurt you!

 
Jessica June 28, 2012 at 1:56 pm

    I dont have any enemies that Im aware about …. am I naive then ???
    Well there is some persons that I dont understand and that just dissapeared from my life without an explanation ….. I would love a answer why.
    But they are not enemies …. what should I call them ??
    Anyhow I think they are cowards that cant tell the truth to me,
    but I have forgive them long ago.
    I just understand and that can haunt my mind from time to time.

    Love and hugs Jessica

   

    Jessica June 28, 2012 at 1:57 pm

        I just dont understand and that can haunt my mind from time to time.

heart June 28, 2012 at 1:34 pm

    Forgive enemies, but stay away from them. They say to keep your friend close, but your enemy closer. Yes, if you are dishonest. There is pretended close, where you stay with an enemy, because it is the lesser of two evils. And, really every person on this earth is both a friend, and perhaps a bit of an enemy, including ourself. In my own experience, I used to let people bulldoze over me. Not anymore. Now I bulldoze if I have to get rid of a bugger.. It’s all these who exaggerate your mistakes, or accuse you of false stuff. I’ve found every person does mistakes, so if they attack me, I’m right back at them, HARD..
    Of course, I try most of the time to be a good example to praise others, and contribute every day to a friendly environment, and making people feel good about themself..

 
ngl68 June 28, 2012 at 10:39 am

    A proposito di perdono mi viene in mente una frase storica di un grande presidente degli Stati Uniti d’America J.F. Kennedy che dice “Perdona i tuoi nemici ma non dimenticare i loro nomi”.

    Buona riflessione.

  
Heimo Alexander Kruschinski June 28, 2012 at 10:15 am

    It is indeed rightly, cited by some, a biblical passage. “Father forgive them for they know not what they do.” What they really mean? One could interpret it. “They know not what they do.” You could say they are like children. Stupid. No, kids are not stupid. That can not be what he have meant. He says they are complete idiots. They have no consciousness. The world has changed little since that day, no? “Father, forgive them.” He asks for forgiveness. He does not say. “Father, I forgive them”. Apart from that, it is the last moment of his life. I know of Bible passages in which Jesus was very angry where I see no forgiveness. It seems to be a process. Something that has led him to this point. If he has really given forgivness for everyone why he comes back as a judge? It’s judgement is not longer necessary. Everyone interprets things in a separate way. Right is the one who has the majority. So is life. But the majority can fail, that is also a part of life. Otherwise they would not have crucified him.

    I wish you all a wonderful day

 

    Annie June 28, 2012 at 5:10 pm

        I believe that Jesus said “Father, forgive them because…” and in this it is implied that he forgives them too..At least that’s the way I see it.. because when you ask God to forgive someone that hurt you, it implies that you also forgive that someone…
        Also, one can also understand from that passage that forgiveness is a divine attribute..

        Have a wonderful day too!
        Love and Gratitude
        Annie

    katie June 28, 2012 at 9:53 pm

        true, annie, wise & old soul <3: "forgiveness is a divine attribute.."

        I needed to develop my spiritual side to be able to see my enemies and the hostile situations in a different way. it is as if eyes are opening; I begin to understand the situation and all our parts in it. it is the understanding that then leads to being able to forgive. and the moment of forgiving gives me back a spiritual richness affecting the way I feel, enjoy and live life, and also can connect to others.

    Heimo Alexander Kruschinski June 28, 2012 at 9:58 pm

        The “because” I do not see. Jesus knew exactly what he says. The rest is interpretation. You can also say he leaves the decision to God. He asks, but he does not forgive. I see forgiveness rather in the feminine aspect. The mother of Jesus. A mother whose son was killed. It is surely not by chance that she is the woman of the roses and always put people first. She helps souls when everything is dark. She forgives and prays for us. Jesus will judge us if you believe the Bible. Is perhaps a coincidence that this wonderful prayerof forgivness Hilal has spoken, and not Paulo. I do not know. Of course these are thoughts and opinions.

        I wish you a wonderful evening

    Annie June 29, 2012 at 10:06 am

        for they know not what they do, is the because dear Heimo/. That’s English.. it’s not interpretation… http://www.englisch-hilfen.de/en/words/because_as_since_for.htm

        of course He knows what he says.. but do you know what He says? or understand? that’s the question……..
        As for the feminine aspect , in many things, Jesus was acting with such compassion for the ignorant, you could say this was his feminine side… this is one of the occasion.. but don’t exclude the other , darker, part of the feminine. feminine is not only the compassion, it’s the other side too..

        Lastly I believe we are out of context for this post…
        this post is about forgiveness for our own sake… if you believe in God, then the forgiveness and anything you do, here forgiving, is between you and God.. (that is also another reason why Jesus asks God) . It’s never between you and the other people, it’s always you and the Divine, or if you don’t believe in God, then it’s between you and the Higher Self of you… it’s never between you and others…that is for whatever you do.. for everything you do in life

        Have a great day!

Jane Stewart (Dances With Crayons) June 28, 2012 at 8:58 am

    Dear Paulo, thankyou.
    A precious loved one had given up on his dream for a long time. For many years, sometimes during quiet moments, wondered. Times during our togetherness, of ‘falling off the wagon’, seeking to control his actions. Maybe I should have done this, or that.
    But in letting go, hoped, and prayed. Sent love.
    Then, we met again. Your eyes sparkled like a twinkling star, you held my hands and said:
    ‘You could not do it for me….’
    We entered an open space, of acceptance. We bathed in Your waters, of grace. Thankyou God.

    And now, the gift of the present.
    Joy, as the colors dance and play in the water. Like a child, full of love and wonder.
    I forgive, Amen

    Sincerely, Love and Gratitude,
    Jane

  
Souls voice June 28, 2012 at 5:00 am

    Always keep your ” souls voice ” alive as this is what differentiates you from the mob which consists of people who have never met their own soul ….
    I have been talking to my innereself ie souls voice and what i could conclude was ….

    Definitions people have learnt in life are just for the sake of knowledge but not for the sake of wisdom…and There lies the difference i think ie due to absence of Souls Voice or interaction with your own soul …. Which is never wrong as it is connected to soul of the universe the source of wisdom ….. Source of vision …vision clear and immortal …..

  
CarmenMaria June 28, 2012 at 1:29 am

    I guess you have to forgive your enemies ahead of time to have peace of mind and heart.

  
Psalmbody June 27, 2012 at 10:20 pm

    A clean, fragrant heart and Life is p(e)ace beyond understanding or debate.
    Thanks for the continued resonance of your posts!

  
Nelly Nazario June 27, 2012 at 7:08 pm

    Difícil pero liberador.

   
Anthony Olliver June 27, 2012 at 6:47 pm

    Acho que o verdadeiro perdão é exatamente este. Quando a gente perdoa sem sentir raiva. Fazendo um trocadilho do ditado popular digo que quem perdoa ama.

   
Empié June 27, 2012 at 5:35 pm

    Supongo, que el perdón, el fin del amor, el fin del odio, son agenos a nuestra voluntad. Un día todo se pasa, y ya está, intentar acelerar ese proceso es como empujar al río (esto es de Paulo). A veces creemos que lo tenemos todo bajo control y resulta que no, en cualquier caso, me he enfadado con personas buenas y con personas malas, con las buenas me aparto si no puedo controlar mis emociones y espero, con ellas no hay nada que perdonar, a las malas las aparto mientras dura el fuego y después sencillamente las olvido.

    Un saludo, con lo fácil que es decirlo y lo que cuesta hacer que los sentimientos nos obedezcan, la verdad es que creo que van por libre.

    Hasta pronto.

   
Marie-Christine Grimard June 27, 2012 at 3:10 pm

    Jesus on the Cross has interceded with his father, in favor of men who had tortured and finally killed. He said: “Father, forgive them for they do not know what they are doing”.
    To do this one must be at least a saint, or so, a God ..
    Well here is what we mean. To rise to the goodness of God himself by forgiving those who trespass against us.
    It’s hard, very hard.
    I, who am very far from being holy … I can just forget those who made ​​me really hard. Forget, is actually a way to survive. Not to see them.
    But tranformer anger and passion in oblivion, then indifference … is far from true forgiveness.
    In fact, it is a form of contempt.
    Forgiveness may be the next step … But there is much work to extinguish passion. I will try …
    Perhaps, is that it be dead …

    Jésus sur la Croix a intercédé auprès de son père, en faveur des hommes qui l’avaient torturé et finalement, mis à mort. Il a dit: “Mon père, pardonne leur, ils ne savent pas ce qu’ils font !”.
    Pour pouvoir faire cela il faut être au moins, un saint, ou alors, un Dieu..
    Voici bien de quoi nous parlons. De s’élever jusqu’à la bonté de Dieu lui-même en pardonnant à ceux qui nous ont offensé.
    C’est dur, très dur.
    Moi, qui suis très loin d’être sainte … je ne sais qu’oublier ceux qui m’ont fait vraiment du mal. Oublier, en fait est un moyen de survivre. Ne plus les voir.
    Mais tranformer la colère, et la passion, en oubli, puis en indifférence… est très loin du vrai pardon.
    En fait, c’est une forme de mépris.
    Le pardon sera peut-être l’étape suivante… Je vais essayer .
    Mais il reste beaucoup de travail, pour éteindre la passion. Peut-être , est-ce cela être mort…

 
gustavo gonzalez June 27, 2012 at 2:43 pm

    Excelente artículo, las enseñanzas de Dios deben ser practicadas todos los dias, aun cuando sean dias buenos, porque eso reforzará aun más nuestra conviccion de ayudarnos y ayudar a otros.

    Saludos
    Gracias Paulo por transmitir estos mensajes

  
Kealan June 27, 2012 at 1:21 pm

    May be one of the things about life, is forgiving those who have decided not to forgive you. That way the warrior can move forward, and leave those clutching to the past, in the past.

   

    Susana June 27, 2012 at 2:49 pm

        Kealan hi, I like this! Simply because it means we can get back to being in the moment again, creating afresh… free ..to be…to create. All the best xx

    Kealan June 28, 2012 at 2:01 am

        hi Susana!

        For sure, there is no point in waiting for other people to catch up with your life. Smile, say good bye and keep moving. Life is too short to be dragged down. I have learned from personal experience.

toñi June 27, 2012 at 11:49 am

    Me viene algo al pensamiento: “las personas que más difícil nos resulta querer…son aquellas personas que más necesitan nuestro amor”.
    A veces nos resulta muy difícil querer a los demás, o los demás nos lo ponen difícil y podemos pensar “esta persona me odia, la ha tomado conmigo, pero no es así…en realidad esa persona actua de la forma que lo hace porque en realidad “necesita mucho amor, necesita sentirse mejor”. A veces, si cambiamos de perspectiva podemos descubrir otro modo de ver las cosas. Es curioso, escribo este mensaje mientras un montón de personas chillan y pelean a mi alrededor, y pelean por tonterías ¡claro!, les falta …amor. Y yo aqui, escribiendo este mensaje como si nada en este mundo o el mundo que me rodea me importase una mierda. (perdón por mi falta de educación).
    Un saludo,
    Toñi.

    
Annie June 27, 2012 at 11:14 am

    Should one forgive his enemies when they still do things to hurt him?
    I always thought that this is a tough question to answer.. but I ve come to believe yes.. they might do whatever they like… I really don’t care!
    the thing is when you detach that person a bit, if lets say isyour father or mother or sister or lover or whatever and put the relationship aside, as if it was any other man or woman to whom there is no family or friendly or romantic relationship, then it’s just as any other man, so your ego really doesn’t care at all, it’s so easy then…
    so I ve come to believe yes…. I do not feel hatred for them either..nor am I angry …
    but it surely is refreshing and liberating to forgive , it frees you from them.. it detaches you and it frees you …

    Viva Freedom = Love

    Love and Gratitude
    Annie

   

    Olta Canka June 27, 2012 at 1:27 pm

        Maybe I am confusing things here… but forgiving, to me, isn’t the same as detaching. To me, the act of forgiveness requires compassion.
        What you describe here seems to me that it is not the same as truly relieving, freeing, but exiling those people from your life.
        You say you feel no anger nor hatred for them, but I believe that in forgiving, one will also leave room for love after that: loving their enemy.
        This is why, to me, it makes forgiveness not that easy and maybe, sometimes, even impossible

    Tarek June 27, 2012 at 2:24 pm

        True dear Annie! Though others can be the “cause/tools” of me being in pain or anger, at the end it is ME who get hurt or angry. Consequently, it is ME who have to solve the problem of my own anger, hatred and pain instead of blaming the tools “the reason”. My pain and anger is always inside me and not anywhere else! ♥

    Annie June 27, 2012 at 4:03 pm

        @dear Olta,
        no! forgiving is NOT the same with detaching.. though detaching IS a kind of cutting the chains you were chained..you are cutting the cord..and you can either forgive then or not.. you leave it in the past, where it belongs.. you decide not to be labeled by this past or by that action which hurt you or by whatever.
        For me, detaching helped me forgive.. i detached from the past (includes detaching from who you were too, and your ego, which includes your reactions to what ‘bothered’ you) so whatever happened it couldn’t apply to the now, the present, and every minute from that on, because every minute it’s a different present. Also another detachment; sometimes it helps if I detach the people who are very dear to me from their actions that hurt me, I used to excuse them always because I loved them but that it didn’t help.. it DID help to detach their actions..because they possibly are not aware hurting me, but even if they are, well then it still helps me to detach that annoying action from the person..
        Oh, Olta I cannot forgive If I don’t love.. I do love them but that doesn’t mean I liked what they ve done…
        and to be totally honest, I was TAUGHT forgiveness, and I was taught how it is to be loved, when I was forgiven for something… till then I was throwing all what hurt me in a dark pit and not actually forgave…
        .Compassion is a very potent word.. it includes passion, one really engages his heart along with the other person , which is not easy.. It’s a whole process and not just an action

        As dear Tarek points out, it is YOUR anger or pain, noone can feel it but you, and noone can solve it but you, it is your problem, the other person might not even imagine the hurt that did to you..so when not solved, you need duct tape all over..,certainly it’s wasting time to relish on the hurt or the pain or the anger..
        As I always imagined it, when you feel anger or hatred, it’s like biking and your bike carries chains all over, which one : makes you go slower, two, it’s very noisy and not at all stylish :), and three: you cannot go very far..

        the most important thing, believe, nothing is impossible <3

        Love and Gratitude
        Annie

    LoveM June 27, 2012 at 6:03 pm

        YES Annie I love that clarity..
        It does detach you from those aspects of a named relationship..
        That bring expectation.. dependency.. neediness.. minding.. irritation.. blaming.. accusing..
        But still allows for positive human interaction.. respect.. cooperation.. enjoyment.. friendship.. love..
        But also the realisation all human failing is the result of the other not knowing or being able to be any better because if they did they would..
        This innocent view saves yourself and your world from endless misery and recrimination..
        You remain in harmony and at peace inside yourself..
        Blessings LoveM <3

    Olta Canka June 27, 2012 at 10:41 pm

        These two last years, when I participated to the rituals at the church, before Easter eve, when we remembered the moments when Jesus died on the cross, I saw his wooden image hanging on the cross, I was moved and I said to myself: “My God, until now I used to think I can forgive so easily, that my heart can so easily be freed from hatred, and I felt so proud of that, but I realized that to really forgive it takes much more. Look at this man on the cross! Forget for a few instants that he is God, and see his human side. I see a human in pain and yet forgiving so easily, washing me and them through his pure love. He is forgiving me for me, he is giving me his love, and he is not doing that for himself to be free since he is going through his destiny, he has now accomplished everything and it seems that nothing is holding him back. No kind of pain. He doesn’t even have to do it, if it were for him, he is doing that for me.
        How can I understand this?
        My dear God, have I ever really forgiven in my entire life?
        I that I thought I knew what and how, I know now that I know nothing at all.”

        Love
        Olta

    LoveM June 28, 2012 at 12:39 pm

        Dear Olta.. knowing nothing is the best place to be.. it allows you to give up all the ideas, thoughts and beliefs you have about Life and God.. so that you can experience this moment in pure.. fresh.. open.. naked innocence..
        It is a beautiful.. wondrous.. mystery that is founded in peaceful.. joyful.. loving being.. free of all blame.. recrimination.. sin and separation.. AtOne with what is.. your essential nature.. which is just Divine Presence.. seeing loving and enjoying Itself.. BelovedOne.. LoveM

    Annie June 28, 2012 at 5:22 pm

        Dear Olta, how can you understand forgiveness you ask…
        The best thing to understand anything is to do it yourself <3 there is no better lesson than that I believe..
        to understand love you need..to love
        to understand forgiveness, you need to forgive
        to understand anything, you need to do that anything..
        How can you understand swimming if you don't swim?
        How can you understand how it is to feel happy or sad if you don't know how it is to be happy or sad..
        I think you get the idea ;)

        WHat's done is done.. you cannot have a better past. That's done. but you can choose to have a better present and even better future <3
        Forgiving does not erase the past. If something is healed , it doesn't mean there wasn't a wound there.. it means choosing to transmute that past into something better.. that is your present and your future, which will become present ;)
        with all my love

        Love and Gratitude
        Annie

Elda June 27, 2012 at 11:12 am

    Yeahhh thank you for this great post…
    To spread love everywhere is the best thing that everyone of us could do..Key of having a wonderful life full of joy and happiness is unhaving enemies ond if we have we must forgive them because and God said Forgive them because the dont know what are doing.


ngl68 June 27, 2012 at 10:41 am

    …perdonate e vi sarà perdonato, date e vi sarà dato, una buona misura , pigiata, scossa e traboccante vi sarà versata nel grembo, perchè con la misura con cui misurate, sarà misurato a voi in cambio.
    Luca 6.37

 
Olta Canka June 27, 2012 at 10:39 am

    I think forgiveness is one of the most important orders that Jesus gave us.
    So simple but hard to do.
    He died on the cross and yet asked for us to be forgiven.
    Forgiveness is a mystery to me.

  
Oceane June 27, 2012 at 10:00 am

    Pardonner est une Force..et parfois cette force nous abandonne quand on a subi des tors et des blessures qui détruisent la santé ,la carrière professionnelle ,la famille,les relations,les amis qui nous sont chers…il existe des pervers capables de vous détruire tout cela d’un seul coup…Dieu seul sait combien c’est dur et long de refaire surface….pardonner pour mieux se porter et se libérer de ce poids qu’on traine ,et continuer de mener sa “vie” tant bien que mal…ma force est ma prière et ma lecture du Livre Saint Le Coran…mais c’est vrai. Si on demande a chaque prière ,a Dieu de nous pardonner nos fautes, pourquoi .nous,humains ,infiniment petits ,devant l’infiniment grand,ne le ferions -nous pas…..il faut pardonner….merci Paulo…

   
Heimo Alexander Kruschinski June 27, 2012 at 8:48 am

    A beautiful story. It is certainly true that what the monk says his pupil. The answer of the student would be interesting. Well, if I were a vicious pupil, which of course – thank God – I am not, I would say the following.
    “I am learning hard Master. Mr. Coelho, in his book “The Pilgramage” says that it is sufficient to be a drunkard and pray every day three Hail Marys to get into the light. We should open a brewery. Everyone is praying three Hail Mary gets a free beer. This work, God will not forget and the perfume of it will even satisfy his angels.”
    Whether the monk forgive his pupil, I do not know. Each Master has just the pupil that he deserves, and vice versa. Is surely something spiritual.

    I wish you all a wonderful day

   
Tumko na bhool paayenge ..... June 27, 2012 at 8:36 am

    Paulo you are requested to intervene and end this episode here only . For now people are more inclined to personal rivalries and are purely working on a fixed mindset are not interested in solutions or positive results rather are purely going wild and out of controls. They are defeating the purpose of this debate . It was fine until now was result oriented had a very positive outcome but now i find it may end up into a mess due to certain destructive and complex brains working on the Blog… Yesterday i have checked your blog on my lappy i found that its only working on my pc and cell . How is it possible ? has this something to do with cyber crime like cracking of email password or transfer of other relevant data from my computers …

   
Marie-Christine June 27, 2012 at 8:19 am

    it feels good,
    thank you for the present.
    with love
    Marie-Christine

   
nazario hofstetter oyarzabal June 27, 2012 at 8:16 am

    thank you :)

  
Tumko na bool paayenge ..... June 27, 2012 at 7:44 am

    I loved it …. Have read it again n again…. I feel there are people who are not able to forgive their friends too …. For them forgiving enemies can be still bigger task …. Its all due to holding on …. Lets first start with ‘ letting go’ the things we are holding on…. Lets forgive each other . God forgive me for the people i have hurt and pray to provide us enough strength to forgive others …… Better lets depart from here ….. No ill feelings for each others ….. Friends…..forever….. No more blog …… Bye …… Every one….

   
Varah Katims June 27, 2012 at 7:07 am

    It takes a lot of courage to forgive. But after all it brings us peace & relief…

   
THELMA June 27, 2012 at 5:31 am

    The ultimate act of LOVE is .. forgiveness. It is the Katharsis of our Psyche from hatred and feelings of revenge!
    ‘ Father, forgive them; they do not know what they are doing’ were His last words. He showed us the Way. The way to stop the Circle. The Ladder to Heaven.
    LOVE,
    Thelma xxx

   
Tumko na bool paayenge ..... June 27, 2012 at 2:41 am

    If you go to the routes of forgiving others or enemies its not that you are not forgiving them … Its you are not forgiving yourself … You are holding on something which is not allowing you to forgive them . that sense & act of letting go is the key to forgiving others which we also call forgiving our ownself . So Let it Go ….

    ” Close your eyes …. Clean your Heart …. And let it Go….”

    Try this formula it works ….

    The best part of forgiving is you yourself reward your own noble act …. By becoming free from bondage of holding on …. So reward yourself …. Try it …. I did …. Now its your turn…. The difference only is in place of enemies here its my friends whome i have forgiven….

Paulo Coelho July 30, 2012 at 10:06 pm

    what happened?

 
