Paulo Coelho's Blog

Vacations!

by Paulo Coelho on July 17, 2012

Although I enjoy my work a lot (once I tweeted: “if you do what you love, every day is a holiday”) I need to stop being in front of the computer – and this is the main reason for taking vacations.

I will be back by the end of August. Suphi, my webmaster, will be moderating comments. Comments in Portuguese will take longer to be moderated, as I will access the blog only once a day.
As “Manuscrito encontrado em Accra” will be released on the 25th of July, its page will be constantly updated.
But the main page of the blog will not.

If it happens you are visiting this blog for the first time, please check the ARCHIVES

Love

Paulo


!@#$%^&*() COMMENTS


Natalia July 31, 2012 at 8:28 pm

    Ayer empecé a leer el alquimista y hoy lo terminé. Siempre tus libros me atrapan y me hacen sentir algo inexplicable, me llenan de fe, de esperanza y hasta de alegría. Muchisimas gracias

   
Susana July 31, 2012 at 4:43 pm

    Enjoy Vacations!!!!!!!!
    returns with batteries recharged
    to delight us with your creativity

    thankssssss

    
toñi July 31, 2012 at 8:39 am

    Creo que sería interesante hablar sobre el tema del egoismo. Todo el mundo utiliza esta palabra y la utilizan para luego pedir favores a los demás. Te sueltan un discurso y después te piden algo. Si no les das lo que quieres entonces te dicen “egoista” “no me extraña que nadie te quiera”. Y digo yo…no es más egoista aquel que nunca hace nada por nadie y solo se acuerda de los demás para pedirles cosas? No creo que una persona que no se dedica a molestar a los demás ni les pide nada, sea egoista por no querer ayudar a los demás cuando nunca se acuerdan de esa persona, simplemente para pedirle cosas. Creo que esta palabra del egoismo es una palabra que se utiliza mucho para la “manipulación psicológica o emocional”. He cambiado mi forma de pensar y de sentir, puede ser que sea egoismo, pero desde luego no pienso cambiar de opinión. Cuando yo estaba sola, nadie estaba conmigo. Si ahora son los demás los que están solos…supongo que el resultado de sus vidas es el resultado de su actitud y comportamiento. Ya no utilizo mi energía para los demás, ya no soy donante de sangre, tengo que cuidar al número uno. Porque cada persona es responsable de su vida y de sus problemas también.
    Un saludo y un abrazo Paulo,
    Toñi.

   
ekta July 30, 2012 at 12:15 pm

    hi…..i don’t know with whom i can share so i am writing to you. i also don’t know whether you will read it and reply me back or not (though i really want you to) but still i am writing it here as i find no other way to communicate with you
    i have never been the nervous kinds and i have this very important interview coming up in 3 days and for the first time i am nervous as hell. i have to touch up on a lot of topics to be well prepared.and i also understand i have to keep my cool and be focused and concentrated. but i am not able to focus on anything and be able to relax. its one of a kind situation and i am really hating it. its kind of some of vicious circle i am stuck in. maybe writing about it will help me vent out my negative feelings and focus more on the positiveness of the situation and try and appreciate it and be thankful about it.
    i would be thankfull if you can advice me on this.

    
Анна July 29, 2012 at 2:19 pm

    Думаю,что со смыслом рождаешься, и несешь скорбь всю свою жизнь имея любовь в сердце видишь и возвышаешься. Благодарю!

    
Dont you know July 29, 2012 at 12:51 pm

    A mans got to do what a mans got to do.
    Enjoy
    Pauline

    
Atreyu July 28, 2012 at 10:33 pm

    Supongo que no se puede ver el mundo desde un agujero, para ver el conjunto en su totalidad hay que salir fuera, si no solo se ve un poquito, y si se quiere interpretar la realidad con solo unos pocos fragmentos, la interpretación será errónea.

    Un saludo, hace tiempo que se que no soy el que seré, hace tiempo que se que las personas son influenciables, hace tiempo que se que la verdad es la verdad.

    Un saludo.

    
Homo conscius July 27, 2012 at 10:31 pm

    And why not stop being in front of the computer until the end of august?

   
toñi July 27, 2012 at 8:27 pm

    Un cuento que me acabo de inventar ahora mismo (bueno hace un rato), me ha venido al pensamiento.
    Una vez un gran sabio entró en un lugar sagrado porque quería hablar con un maestro. Dicho maestro había alcanzado la iluminación tiempo atrás y…estaba trabajando en sus cosas.
    Entonces el sabio se acercó a él y le dijo “he venido a ver como estás” y el maestro le contestó “éste lugar es sagrado, has entrado sin pedir autorización y te preocupas por como estoy… ¿qué quieres?” Entonces el sabio le contestó “un corazón nuevo” y tras unos minutos de silencio el maestro le contestó….
    Aqui termina el primer capítulo de mi cuento. Igual algún día me dedico a escribir cuentos.
    Buenas noches. Un abrazo.
    Toñi.

   

    Atreyu July 28, 2012 at 12:47 pm

        Quiero más.

        Un abrazo.

Marie-Christine July 26, 2012 at 9:40 pm

    I am currently having an end of Festival Radio France vacations…. In case you are wondering.:) tudo bem
    Boarding the tram, I noticed the name ‘Marie de Montpellier’ :)
    We are now entering the theater … just imagine
    The place got packed ..in no time.

    On the menu, some of the contemporary work of the’ Slave’ music. and others was on public display for all to hear.
    We had a duo , a trio , 16 singers , another pianist and Noelle Geny directing the Choeur de l’Opera National de Montpellier.

    A ‘revolutionnaire’ at the start mumbled something and was promptly settled by the management.

    The violonist, pianist and the violoncelle stroking sparkles of each others, gave a spectacular finale.
    ‘Summer time’ was one of the highlight.
    Needless to say….it was just for me ….for the duration, yes, I made it personal :) What thrill it was.
    The most beautiful piece I have ever heard.
    What talent!.
    The last piece from’ Rakma ninoff’ and I melted away.
    ‘Slave’ you say
    No..just liberated
    It just ended being S ‘L’AVE’

    Oops the names If you haven’t already seen them. Dont miss them they are sensational
    I feel privileged because I had already seen Nicolas Dautricourt and Jean-Frederic Neuburger before,
    Nicolas Dautricourt , violin and I like the sense of humour as well
    Jean-Frederic Neuburger, piano
    Alexandre Dmitriev, violoncelle
    Thank you so much.

    Love to you all
    Beijos to Paulo and Cristina
    nice Summer holidays
    Marie-Christine

    
Noel Elizabeth Deyoung July 26, 2012 at 3:03 pm

    Enjoy! Peace be with you,brother.

    
Cherie Roe Dirksen July 26, 2012 at 2:49 pm

    Enjoy your holiday!

    
Shelley July 25, 2012 at 11:38 pm

    I hope you’re somewhere where no phone rings.

    
ALEJANDRA July 25, 2012 at 10:34 pm

    CENTRADO EN UNO MISMO, QUIERE DECIR EN NUESTRO EJE, CENTRADOS EN LA VIDA, SABER QUE QUEREMOS P/ NUESTRA VIDA, EL ESTAR BIEN CON TU PAREJA , UNA SERIE DE COSAS QUE SE TRABAJAN DESDE UNO MISMO P/ PODER PROYECTARSE A LOS DEMAS Y ENTREGAR LO MEJOR QUE TENEMOS .SIGA ESCRIBIENDO COSAS TAN LINDAS PAULO, QUE SU MENTE DESCANSE P/ CONTINUAR CON ESTA MARAVILLOSA OBRA .ATTE. ALEJANDRA SOSA.

    
ALEJANDRA July 25, 2012 at 10:23 pm

    LE DESEO UNAS FELICES VACACIONES !!! LA VERDAD QUE SE LAS MERECE , UNO SABE CUANDO TOMARSELAS , REALMENTE DISFRUTAR DE UN VIAJE , ESTAR EN PAZ CON UNO MISMO.
    NO SIRVE DE NADA IR A LUGARES LEJANOS CUANDO NO SE ESTA CENTRADO EN UNO MISMO.
    AHORA ESTOY ESTUDIANDO , ME VA M. BIEN , CUANDO TERMINE , ME PREMIARE , ME TOMARE MIS DIAS DE DESCANSO , SIN COMPU, VIDA AL AIRE LIBRE .UN FUERTE ABRAZO Y FELICIDADES P/ SU ESPOSA.ATTE. ALEJANDRA.

    
Jessica July 25, 2012 at 5:57 pm

    I hope you will have a wonderful vacation … myself I have vacation because im unemployed right now …. but that will change soon I hope …. I like to work too.

    Love and light Jessica

    
Adriana July 24, 2012 at 8:12 pm

    Querido Paulo!

    Disfruta cada segundo!!! Mil bendiciones!!!! :)
    <3

    
Susana July 24, 2012 at 7:47 pm

    ..sure you are having a wonderful holiday..it is a time of year when hopefully we can all find some time..to be restful.
    My family and I have booked ferry tickets and hotel..for 3 days on the island of Ithaca.. I’m so excited as it will be precious time to unwind and enjoy the newness of these holy days! ..May be we’ll bump into Penelope, or Odysseus even, but I will be happy just to be on this magical Greek island.

    All the very best to you on your jollies! KALO TAXIDI ! XX

    
Linda July 24, 2012 at 2:26 pm

    Dear Paulo,

    Enjoy your holiday, where will you go?
    I am on holiday myself now in beautiful Zurich, Switzerland, however a painful one unfortunatly.
    Let me know if you are ever in Norway or Sweden and I would like to invite you and your wife for some drinks and talks, and share my story, I will be the ” King of the Night” :)

    Linda

    
Marylyn July 24, 2012 at 1:01 pm

    enjoy your vacation Paulo :)

    
Alex July 23, 2012 at 6:14 pm

    Olá, haverá sessão de autógrafos do novo livro no Rio de Janeiro? Quando e onde vai ser? obrigado!

    
Poeta dos Mares July 23, 2012 at 1:35 am

    Paulo, você pode achar coisa de louco, mas estava pensando sobre a promoção do “nosso” (seu e de seus leitores) livro e achei o premio um tanto frio, um “computador”…sabe, acho que seria muito legal, incluir o premio de 10 livros autografados por você. Desculpe Paulo, mas acho que um livro seu, para a maioria de seus seguidores, autografado por você, seria muito mais valioso, afinal de contas, você não para, esta sempre em movimento e fico imaginando a quantidade de leitores que gostariam de receber esse presente, pode parecer pouco pra você, mas seria muito mais valioso que qualquer computador no mundo…

    Desculpe amigo, estava lavando a louça do jantar e uma coisa insistiu e muito para escrever isso a você. Loucura ou não, esta feita a sugestão.

    Poeta dos Mares



    Paulo Coelho July 23, 2012 at 1:43 am

        sugestao atentida. Se eu nao tiver os livros aqui, mando camisetas autografadas.

Aman July 22, 2012 at 9:52 pm

    Even we got a lot to learn from this post.. That, in your words, “A warrior of light rests, but is always alert”..
    Thank you Sir..
    Have Blessed Holidays.. :-)

    
Sascha July 21, 2012 at 5:45 pm

    Paulo, have a nice and relaxing vacation! It’s true, it is kinda fun and relaxed working with a job you love. But vacations are necessary and Iam just one week before it! :-) Happy holiday!

    
Trish July 21, 2012 at 5:56 am

    Happy Holidays!!!!! Have a wonderful break :)

    
Atreyu July 20, 2012 at 11:09 am

    Bonito mundo, pasadlo bien, a mi me queda un poco para estar de vacaciones, pero solo un poco.

    Hasta pronto.

    
Leandro July 20, 2012 at 3:34 am

    Paulo , apenas me responda , por favor !!!

    Você continuará com os textos no blog do g1 ? Vou entrar em abstinência kkkk
    : )

    Por mais que não dê tempo de eu postar um comentário todos os dias , não fico um dia sem ler seus textos lá . Por favor , lhe suplico , ( sei que este é um momento de descaso seu ) , mas ao menos no g1 , continue enviando os textos , eu , o Francisco e todo o pessoal por lá ficaremos muitos felizes .

    Do seu jovem discípulo que ainda não conheceu o mestre pessoalmente .
    Leandro Domingues .
    ( Por enquanto ainda não nos conhecemos , quando eu alcançar minha lenda pessoal no ano que vem , vou à seu encontro para lhe agradecer pessoalmente , nem que eu tenha que ir a Suíça ) .

    
Howard Sherman July 20, 2012 at 12:48 am

    Have a wonderful vacation! Without technology to tie you down I’m sure you’ll return to your keyboard rejuvenated. Enjoy and all the best!

    
mary July 19, 2012 at 10:43 pm

    I hope ye have a great break.Your regular advice and stories will be missed by me and more. I have become addicted to your blog which is a good thing. Thank you for so much stuff.

    
Ankur Tripathi July 19, 2012 at 4:03 pm

    Please tell the destination Sir..

    
Shine July 19, 2012 at 2:18 pm

    Happy vacations Paulo. :) will miss you :) love Avantika

   
Seema July 19, 2012 at 1:40 pm

    Hmm, I wanna go on vacations again, I wanna. Even though I just had in the month of May.

    
Vina July 19, 2012 at 12:55 pm

    Happy holiday paulo. To indonesia? :D

    
Rebecca Constance July 19, 2012 at 12:10 pm

    Wish u have happy vacation days…

    
Varah Katims July 19, 2012 at 7:50 am

    Have a wonderful time Paulo & Christina…

    
Dinorah July 19, 2012 at 5:46 am

    Saudade de seus comentários desde já! Mas todos precisamos desse momento para reenergizar!
    Que o lançamento do livro seja um sucesso e que no seu retorno tenhamos muitas historias a compartilhar!
    Love always!

   
mariana July 19, 2012 at 4:26 am

    happy holiday sir! hope you enjoy it and come back with inspiring stories :)

    
janine v. baldovino July 19, 2012 at 2:44 am

    enjoy your vacation sir!!have fun!!

    best regards,

    Janine

    
Flechis July 18, 2012 at 11:16 pm

    Hi Paulo. How are you doing? I’m an English teacher and I like teaching although it’s not my favourite thing above all.

    
LexoKat July 18, 2012 at 8:51 pm

    Have a nice holiday! Enjoy!

   
Jane Stewart (Dances With Crayons) July 18, 2012 at 7:42 pm

    Hugs and Kisses Paulo and Christina,
    Have a wonderful vacation!!
    Love and Blessings,
    Jane