Paulo Coelho's Blog

13 July: Viva Rosa Mystica!

by Paulo Coelho on July 13, 2012

Whenever you have time, and if you believe in miracles, I encourage you to visit the Rosa Mystica shrine, in Montechiari, Italy
To find more information about the apparitions, please CLICK HERE


!@#$%^&*()  COMMENTS


Wanderlaini Aparecida Rodrigues July 18, 2012 at 10:16 pm

    É um tanto misterioso para mim.

    
ashray July 16, 2012 at 6:30 pm

    Sad but I know nothing about Catholic Church so this is kind of a new thing. Well never too late to get to know about.

    
Bebel Chaves Angra July 15, 2012 at 1:24 am

    Eu acredito em milagres!

    Querido Paulo: ontem eu escrevi aqui que iria orar para Nossa Senhora da Rosa Mística. Minha mãe que tem alzheimer estava sem falar desde ontem, não conheguia se manter de pé e achei que iríamos perdê-la a noite passada.
    Mas após receber um e-mail dizendo que você iria estar na Webcam no dia da Rosa Mística, algo aconteceu. Entrei no teu blog e vi escrito: “Sempre que tiver tempo, e se você acredita em milagres…” Essa frase me tocou profundamente. Orei com toda força da minha alma e hoje pela manhã, quando eu e meu pai acordamos, minha mãe estava bem. Como se nada tivesse acontecido.
    Obrigada meu querido amigo, Deus te usou para me dar uma luz e renovar minhas forças…
    Fique na paz :)
    Bebel Chaves(De Angra dos Reis)

   
Bebel Chaves Angra July 15, 2012 at 1:20 am

    Querido Paulo: ontem eu escrevi aqui que iria orar para Nossa Senhora da Rosa Mística. Minha mãe que tem alzheimer estava sem falar desde ontem, não conheguia se manter de pé e achei que iríamos perdê-la a noite passada.
    Mas após receber após receber por e-mail que iria estar na Webcam no dia da Rosa Mística, algo aconteceu. Entrei no teu blog e vi escrito: “Sempre que tiver tempo, e se você acredita em milagres…” Essa frase me tocou profundamente. Orei com toda força da minha alma e hoje pela manhã, quando eu e meu pai acordamos, minha mãe estava bem. Como se nada tivesse acontecido.
    Obrigada meu querido amigo, Deus te usou para me dar uma luz e renovar minhas forças…
    Fique na paz :)
    Bebel Chaves(De Angra dos Reis)

  
Elena July 14, 2012 at 9:52 pm

    thank you! I’m from Italy, but i didn’t know about that
    another place put in my list of places to go.

    thanks
    With Love

    Elena

   
Dennis Kemper July 14, 2012 at 7:57 pm

    Dear Paolo Coelho,

    This isn’t something for the blog, its a question:

    I’m a 37 year old engenieer (architect) who wants to become a writer as wel.

    because 1′ve read a handfull of books you wrote, and realy liked them, I would like to invite you to have lunch or dinner. When you’re in Holland or Belgium,
    On my costs. To talk about life and writing.

    I think you get loads of invititions, so it would be a mirracle that you woud mail me. but on the other hand: you,ve got to make space to let a mirracle happen.

    all the best
    Dennis Kemper

    
Nelly Nazario July 14, 2012 at 6:52 pm

    Recién viaje a Roma. Pero me encantó tanto Italia que lo tendré en cuenta en mi futuro viaje. Gracias por el dato.

    
Bebel Chaves Angra July 14, 2012 at 2:08 am

    Querido Paulo: eu acredito em milagres!
    Vou orar hoje a noite, daqui de minha casa para Nossa Senhora da Rosa mística.
    Fique na paz,

    
Tutti Rivero July 13, 2012 at 10:40 pm

    Tenho 3 rosas *branca,vermelha e amarela* que a Christina me mandou ha mais de 10 anos,guardadas numa caixinha de pedra chilena.Chegaram na hora exata!
    Um lindo presente.

    
Pilar July 13, 2012 at 5:03 pm

    Estimado Paulo: quedo sinceramente agradecida por ésta su publicación.
    Gracias nuevamente.

    
Olta Canka July 13, 2012 at 2:00 pm

    I’ve heard about many apparitions of Mary, and many of them are so shocking, and I believe people truly see this things, but I refuse to believe in her Lord, I refuse to believe her words and commandments.
    Something just doesn’t fit.
    But they say she is beautiful…

    
Marie-Christine July 13, 2012 at 1:43 pm

    Dear Paulo
    I do believe in miracles
    Viva la Rosa Mystica.
    with love

    Marie-Christine

    
Cristina B. July 13, 2012 at 8:56 am

    PS and I’m also the first person who write a message on this subject.
    Fontanelle I’m coming!!!

    
Cristina B. July 13, 2012 at 8:55 am

    This is a tipical sign, Paulo!!!
    just a year a go I met a woman who told me of Fontanelle ( is 150 km from my home).
    I planned to visit it, but I never did.
    Yesterday I thought about that woman, and wondered if she ha solved her problems .
    The thought came to my mind suddenly, as a blizzard in my brain.
    I didn’t know why.
    Today I read in your blog about that place…
    Miracles belong to the path of common people.
    Love
    Cristina

   
cristina cabral July 13, 2012 at 1:57 am

    Rezo o terço da Rosa Mística todos os dias, que Ela nos proteja e abençõe.

Annie July 13, 2012 at 12:16 am

    Noted down to my travel destinations..:)
    my birthday now got a new dimension with Our Lady at Montechiari, thank you!
    Viva Rosa mystica!

    [Perach, on the Feast of the Immaculate Conception of Our Lady, Mary the Mother of God, December 8, 1983.
    ...
    It is my wish that every year, on 8th December, at noon, the HOUR OF GRACE FOR THE WORLD be celebrated . Many divine and bodily graces will be received through this devotion.]

    Love and Gratitude
    Annie

   
Traveler July 13, 2012 at 12:13 am

    Hola Paulo.

    Me encantaria visitar el lugar que comentas…tienes que ser increible.

    Me encanta tu filosofia de vida y comparto muchos pensamientos contigo, pensamientos positivos sobre la vida. Aqui te invito a mi blog, para que le eches un vistazo:

    Adreamerinlife.blogspot.com

    Un abrazo y sigue asi de grande.

    Antonio